And welcome back to the lab.
そして､ ラボにおかえりなさい｡
Here we are in Jupyter Lab and we are going to go into week two.
ここJupyter Labで2週目に入る｡
And we're going to go now to day two.
そして2日目に入る｡
Here we are radio day.
ラジオの日だ｡
Today we will build user interfaces using the outrageously simple Gradio framework.
今日は､ とんでもなくシンプルなGradioフレームワークを使ってユーザー・インターフェースを構築する｡
Prepare for joy.
喜びの準備をしよう｡
There you go.
そうだ｡
We will do some imports.
輸入もするつもりだ｡
And then this magical line import Gradio as GR.
そして､ この不思議なセリフは､ グラディオをGRとしてインポートする｡
And I said oh yeah.
そして私は､ ああそうだと言った｡
So there we go.
そうだ｡
And we load our environment variables in using the usual approach.
そして､ 通常の方法で環境変数をロードする｡
Um, and you'll recognize the next familiar cell, which is the three somewhat analogous commands to
次のおなじみのセルは､ APIを立ち上げて準備するための3つの類似したコマンドだ｡
Okay.
オーケー｡
So, uh, start by setting a system message in a variable, which is going to be the very generic UI,
変数にシステム・メッセージを設定することから始めましょう｡ これは非常に一般的なUIで､
a helpful assistant that is often the kind of standard starting point for a system message.
システム・メッセージの標準的な出発点となることが多い､ 役に立つアシスタントです｡
So that's what we will take.
だから､ 私たちが取るのはそれだ｡
Um, and now we're going to wrap a call to GPT four mini.
さて､ これからGPT4ミニに電話をかける｡
Uh, in a simple function like this, a message GPT takes a prompt messages equals.
ええと､ このような単純な関数では､ メッセージGPTはプロンプトメッセージに等しいものを受け取ります｡
Now, by this point, uh, hopefully you were bored of this structure.
さて､ この時点で､ できればこの構成に飽きていてほしい｡
You know it so well, uh, a simple conversation structure, a list of dictionaries system, a system
シンプルな会話構造､ 辞書のリスト､ システムメッセージ､ ユーザープロンプト､
message user, a user prompt, and then we call completion OpenAI chat, dot completions, dot create.
そしてOpenAIチャットの補完､ ドット補完､ ドット作成｡
We pass in a model and we pass in the messages.
モデルを渡し､ メッセージを渡す｡
And what we return is the completion dot choices.
そして､ 私たちが返すのは完成点の選択肢である｡
We take the first choice dot message content.
私たちは最初の選択肢であるドットメッセージの内容を取る｡
That is a function which we are wrapping to message GPT and return a response.
これは､ GPTにメッセージを送り､ レスポンスを返すためにラップしている関数だ｡
Let's run that.
それを実行しよう｡
Let's just quickly try that out.
さっそく試してみよう｡
What should we say?
何と言うべきか？
Message GPT we've tried a few things that we know spell that right GPT we know what GPT is good at and
メッセージ GPTの得意なこと､ 不得意なことをいくつか試してみた｡
Let's just try one more thing.
もうひとつだけ試してみよう｡
We know that it's not great at current events.
時事問題が苦手なのは知っている｡
Let's just go with something very simple.
とてもシンプルなもので行こう｡
What is today's date and let's see what GPT believes is today's date.
今日の日付は何か､ GPTが考える今日の日付を見てみよう｡
Today's date is October the 3rd, 2023.
今日の日付は2023年10月3日｡
So a few things to note.
そこで､ いくつか注意しておきたいことがある｡
One is that, as expected, it does not have a good sense of current events.
ひとつは､ 予想通り､ 時事問題に対するセンスがないことだ｡
And the second is that it does appear that its training data took it up until October 2023, just the
そして2つ目は､ トレーニングデータが2023年10月まで､
beginning of October, uh, which is something that I alluded to before when it had said September.
つまり10月の初めまで有効だったということだ｡
I thought it was October, but I suppose if it's October the 3rd, then, then maybe it's a moot point.
私は10月だと思っていたが､ 10月3日なら､ それは無意味なことなのかもしれない｡
It's a it's an end of September.
もう9月も終わりだ｡
Early October would be the answer anyways.
いずれにせよ､ 10月初旬が答えだろう｡
That is a very simple function that we've got there.
これはとてもシンプルな機能だ｡
Put that to the back of your mind because we're going to come back to it later.
そのことは頭の片隅に置いておいてほしい｡
It's time to create user interfaces.
ユーザー・インターフェースを作る時だ｡
First of all, nothing to do with data science.
まず第一に､ データサイエンスとは何の関係もない｡
Let's just see how to create a simple user interface.
簡単なユーザー・インターフェースの作り方を見てみよう｡
So here then is a very simple function called shout.
では､ shoutという非常にシンプルな関数を紹介しよう｡
And shout is going to take some text.
そして､ 叫ぶにはテキストが必要だ｡
And it's going to reply with that text in uppercase.
そして､ そのテキストが大文字で返信される｡
That's a pretty simple one.
簡単なことだよ｡
So let's shout hello.
だから､ ハローと叫ぼう｡
And it says back hello and uppercase a shouty way.
そして､ ハローと大文字で怒鳴るように言い返す｡
Um, okay.
うーん､ わかった｡
So I put it to you that building a sophisticated user interface with inputs and outputs that can convert
つまり､ 小さなハローを大きなハローに変換できる入出力を備えた洗練されたユーザー・インターフェースを構築するのは､
a little hello to a big hello, is as simple as this.
これくらい簡単なことなのだ｡
It's a two lines view is great interface.
2行で表示される素晴らしいインターフェイスだ｡
That means I want a new interface.
つまり､ 新しいインターフェイスが欲しいということだ｡
You tell it the function that you want.
欲しい機能を伝えるのだ｡
The function that is this user interface is built around, which in this case is shout.
このユーザー・インターフェースは､ この場合はシャウトを中心に構築されている｡
This function describes right here I'm passing in the function name and what you pass in.
この関数は､ 関数名と何を渡すかをここで説明している｡
You then have to pass in inputs and outputs.
そして､ 入力と出力を渡さなければならない｡
And Gradio is very flexible about what you can pass in here.
そしてグラディオは､ ここでパスできるものに関して非常に柔軟だ｡
You can pass in lists of things if you've got multiple inputs and outputs.
複数の入出力がある場合は､ リストを渡すことができる｡
If you've only got one input and one output, you can just say what kind of thing it is as a string.
入力と出力が1つずつしかない場合は､ それがどのようなものかを文字列で表せばいい｡
That's all it needs.
それだけで十分だ｡
It will figure it all out.
それがすべてを解決してくれる｡
Um, and just because this is two lines of code, but just to show you, we could just do it as one
これは2行のコードですが､ お見せするために1行のコードにすることもできます｡
We can just put it all in one line, uh, and just run that and let's see what happens.
すべてを1行にまとめて､ それを実行して､ どうなるか見てみよう｡
We have ourselves here a little user interface.
私たちはここに小さなユーザー・インターフェイスを持っている｡
I'm going to type hello.
ハローと打つよ｡
And I'm going to press submit.
そして､ 私は送信を押すつもりだ｡
And there is a shouty hello right back at me.
そして､ 私に向かって怒鳴るような挨拶が返ってきた｡
It's a user interface with great controls around it.
素晴らしい操作性を備えたユーザーインターフェースだ｡
And it's all been built running within this uh, this this this, uh, browser, just like that.
そしてそれはすべて､ この､ この､ ブラウザーの中で動いている｡
Now, one thing you might notice is that there's a flag button here, and a folder has been created
ここでひとつお気づきの点があるとすれば､ ここにフラグボタンがあり､ フラグ付きというフォルダが作成されていることだ｡
And this is a feature that comes out of the box with Gradio to allow functionality for users to flag
これは､ 機械学習でよくあるユースケースで､ ユーザーが何が起こっているかを確認し､
your results, which is a kind of common use case with machine learning, where you want users to be
結果に問題があればメモを取ることができるようにしたい場合です｡
But that out of the box functionality is not something we particularly want, and the way we can remove
その代わりに､ フラグを立てることを許可するイコール
that is by passing in allow flagging equals never instead.
"never "を渡すのだ｡
So if I now run that instead, uh, again, I sort of resent the fact that I put that as two lines when
だから今､ その代わりにそれを実行すると､ あー､ 繰り返しになるけど､ このように1行で済ませることも同じようにできたのに､
I could equally well have done it as one line like that, just to really show you how simple it is.
2行にしたことがちょっと恨めしいよ｡
A single line.
一本の線｡
Uh, and here we get, um, our user interface.
そしてここに､ ユーザー・インターフェイスがある｡
Uh, so there's a couple of things I've done about this that I want to mention.
ええと､ それで､ この件に関していくつかやったことがあるんだけど､ それについて言っておきたいことがあるんだ｡
The first of them is with either of these cases, there's also a link that it gives you at the top here.
そのうちのひとつは､ これらのケースのいずれかを選択した場合､ この一番上にリンクが表示されます｡
And if you click on this link, uh, it actually brings up your interface in an entirely separate window
このリンクをクリックすると､ このようにまったく別のウィンドウにインターフェイスが表示される｡
Let's go.
行こう｡
Hello.
こんにちは｡
And it just works.
そして､ うまくいくんだ｡
And that's because when you run Gradio, it actually runs a little web server running in the background.
というのも､ Gradioを実行すると､ バックグラウンドで小さなウェブ・サーバーが動くからだ｡
Uh, running locally at a at whatever the first port it finds that's free.
ええと､ 最初に空いているポートを見つけて､ ローカルで実行するんだ｡
After after some, some number, uh, after, I think 760 is where it begins and it starts going on
何回目か､ 何回目か......760回目くらいからが始まりで､ そこからが本番だと思う｡
from there.
だから､ 最後の1本がそうだったんじゃないかと思う｡
Yeah.
そうだね｡
Was it 760?
760だったか？
Uh, so, um, it will run that little web server.
それで､ その小さなウェブサーバーを動かすんだ｡
And so you can either show that in the same Jupyter notebook in the output, or you can just bring it
同じJupyterノートブックに出力することもできるし､
up in a separate screen in its own right, which is amazing.
別の画面に表示することもできる｡
But even more than that, the other thing I've shown here is that you can pass share equals true into
しかしそれ以上に､ 私がここで示したもう一つのことは､ シェア・イコール・トゥルーを通話に反映させることができるということだ｡
And if you do that, then Gradio also serves the same interface on a public URL that you can share with
そうすれば､ Gradioは同じインターフェイスをパブリックURLで提供し､
other people so that other people, colleagues that you're working with can use your same model and
他の人と共有することができます｡
And this part is a little bit of the mind bending part of it.
そして､ この部分は少し心を曲げる部分でもある｡
When someone brings up this user interface, which we'll do right now, it'll take just a second.
誰かがこのユーザー・インターフェースを表示させたら､ 今すぐにでも表示させることができる｡
There's a bit more going on behind the scenes.
舞台裏ではもう少しいろいろなことが起こっている｡
Here it comes.
来たぞ｡
Here's the user interface.
これがユーザーインターフェースだ｡
It looks it's of course the same as this.
見た目はもちろんこれと同じだ｡
I'll run hello.
こんにちは｡
And we'll see it working.
そして､ それがうまくいくのを見るだろう｡
What's happening here.
ここで何が起きているのか｡
This is of course being served by Gradio.
これはもちろんグラディオが提供している｡
But when you call submit, when you press submit and call the function, that function hello is running
しかし､ submitを呼び出したとき､ submitを押して関数を呼び出したとき､ その関数helloは､
on, on my local box in this Jupyter environment right here.
このJupyter環境の私のローカル・ボックスで実行されている｡
Uh, it's uh, it's a bit crazy.
ちょっとクレイジーなんだ｡
It's still running the code as it's running on my box.
私のボックスで実行されているコードはそのまま実行されている｡
It's just there's a publicly available URL for it.
公開されているURLがあるだけだ｡
It's kind of magic.
一種のマジックだ｡
Uh, let me explain what I mean by that.
ええと､ どういう意味か説明させてください｡
By going back here and printing here.
ここに戻って､ ここに印刷することで
Shout has been called with input.
シャウトがインプットされた｡
So now we are making very clear what's going on.
だから今､ 私たちは何が起こっているのかを明確にしている｡
So when I run that it says shout has been called with input.
だから､ それを実行すると､ shoutが入力で呼び出されたと表示される｡
Hello.
こんにちは｡
So now let's come back here and run this again.
では､ ここに戻ってもう一度実行してみよう｡
So now it's running with this again a public URL.
これでまた公開URLで実行されるようになった｡
Here it comes.
来たぞ｡
I'm going to type.
これから打つよ｡
This is very cool.
これはとてもクールだ｡
And press submit.
そして送信を押す｡
And obviously this is very cool as what comes back.
そして明らかに､ これは非常にクールだ｡
This is this is being hosted by Gradio.
これはグラディオが主催している｡
But again the somewhat remarkable thing is if I come back here and look in my output, you'll see that
しかし､ ちょっと注目すべき点は､ ここに戻って出力を見てみると､ shoutが入力で呼ばれていることだ｡
This is very cool.
これはとてもクールだ｡
So the function that's running is running on my box.
つまり､ 実行されている機能は私のボックスで実行されているのだ｡
The user interface is being served up through a public radio Gradio website, but the code is running
ユーザー・インターフェースは公共ラジオGradioのウェブサイトを通じて提供されているが､ コードは私のローカル・ボックス上で動いている｡
And what that means basically is that you can write models running on your local box, and you can build
つまり､ 自分のローカル・ボックスで動作するモデルを書き､ インターフェイスを構築し､ それを自分のためにローカルに立ち上げることも､
interfaces, and you can either bring them up locally for yourself, or you can share them with others.
他の人と共有することもできるということだ｡
And as people work with those shared user interfaces, it's still calling the code that is running on
そして､ 共有されたユーザー・インターフェイスで作業している人たちは､ 自分のボックス上で動いているコードを信じられないほど便利なものとして呼び出しているのだ｡
And as you can imagine, for collaborating with people and sharing your models and getting your co-workers
そして､ 想像できるように､ 人々と共同作業をしたり､ モデルを共有したり､ 同僚に協力してもらったりするのに､
to to work with you, uh, it couldn't be easier.
これ以上簡単なものはない｡
All right, so let's keep going and show a couple more things.
よし､ では続けてもう2つほど見せよう｡
I'm now going to bring up an interface which is going to specify inputs and outputs.
これから入出力を指定するインターフェイスを表示する｡
And you can see here what I'm doing is I'm saying that the the inputs it's a list.
ここで私がやっていることは､ 入力がリストになっているということだ｡
It's just got one thing in there.
ただ､ 一つだけあるんだ｡
It's a text box.
テキストボックスだ｡
It's got a label your message and it's got six lines.
メッセージのラベルがあり､ 6行ある｡
The outputs is response and it's got eight lines.
出力はレスポンスで､ 8行ある｡
Um, and it's calling the function shout.
そして､ シャウトという関数を呼び出している｡
let's have a look at that and let's bring that up here.
それを見てみよう｡
And it comes up just as you'd expect and make it a bit bigger for you.
そして､ それはあなたが期待するように出てきて､ あなたのために少し大きくする｡
There we go.
これでよし｡
There is a message.
メッセージがある｡
There's a response.
手応えはある｡
I can say hello yet again and I can press submit.
もう一度挨拶をして､ 送信を押すことができる｡
And over here comes the capitalized version.
そしてこっちは大文字バージョン｡
Very easy, nice and configurable.
とても簡単で､ 素晴らしく､ 設定可能だ｡
Looks like a good UI.
良いUIに見える｡
Well, you can probably imagine what I'm going to suggest next.
さて､ 私が次に何を提案するかは想像がつくだろう｡
Wouldn't it be great?
素晴らしいと思わないか？
Wouldn't it be great if you could just replace that word shout with another function?
シャウトという言葉を別の機能で置き換えることができたら素晴らしいと思わないか？
Any function?
何か機能は？
Why not a message GPT function that we wrote earlier?
先に書いたメッセージGPT関数ではダメなのか？
You could just simply replace that word shout with that function, and you'd be able to have a user
シャウトという言葉をその関数に置き換えるだけで､ LLMの上にユーザー・インターフェースを構築することができる｡
Wouldn't that just be great?
それは素晴らしいことだと思わない？
Wouldn't it be great?
素晴らしいと思わないか？
Ha ha.
ハハハ｡
Well, let's have a look.
では､ 見てみよう｡
Let's have a look.
見てみよう｡
Here we go.
さあ､ 始めよう｡
Same.
同じだ｡
Same code.
同じコードだ｡
We've replaced the function.
機能を入れ替えました｡
It's no longer shout.
もはやシャウトではない｡
It's now message GPT.
今はメッセージGPTだ｡
Let's see what happens.
どうなるか見てみよう｡
Let's bring that up in a separate window.
別ウィンドウで表示しよう｡
Here it is.
これだ｡
Please tell me a joke and we will submit that.
ジョークを言ってください｡
And we'll see what comes back.
何が戻ってくるか見てみよう
Why did the Scarecrow win an award?
スケアクロウが受賞した理由は？
Because he was outstanding in his field.
彼はその分野で傑出していたからだ｡
That's a great joke.
いいジョークだね｡
Uh, okay.
ああ､ わかった｡
A great joke from GPT four mini.
GPTフォーミニの素晴らしいジョーク｡
And a great example of how easy it is to make that bigger for you to build a user interface that is
そして､ LLMを舞台裏で使っているユーザー・インターフェースを構築することが､
running using an LLM behind the scenes.
いかに簡単なことかを示す好例だ｡
I hope that you are as overjoyed by this experience as I am.
皆さんも私と同じように､ この経験で大喜びしてほしい｡
I think Gradio is awesome.
グラディオはすごいと思う｡
All right, I will see you next time when we're going to put Gradio to even more good use.
それではまた次回､ グラディオをさらに有効活用するためにお会いしましょう｡